[Music]
what seems to be going on pretty
reliably so far he's finding
relationships of complementarity a tan
mutual correction rather than
adversarial processing variety attempt
to dominate or destroy I know that that
I think for me not only what we're
talking about but the exemplification of
how we're talking and how we're entering
into a relationship how are we we are
reap right or we're reprioritizing we're
moving off of the product and the
position and trying to really move into
process and participation and that's
well that's that's always been very
important to me because as you know I
aspire towards the Socratic ideal but
that is now even more so the case for me
because I see that ability to enact
functional as opposed to dysfunctional
and adaptive as opposed to maladaptive
collective intelligence and bring it
into something like collective
rationality so that it can effectively
so that we can effectively aspire to
collective rationality and wisdom um
that has become has become very very
central to me and like so that the
process of all this discussion over the
last year meeting all of you guys and
women and then engaging in the work on
the after Socrates project as all as
just it has intensified and very
dramatically deep and it was already
deep I believe but is then intensified
and dramatically deepened my commitment
to the Socratic ideal deilogos that has
now become mmm sort of very very I would
say that sacred to me and the way I talk
about in this series right okay if
you've already breached on some aren't
breached you've already touched on some
of the things that we were going to
discuss the first being rationality and
so you said you said collective
rationality yeah oh so that seemed to be
an interesting idea
and dial logos so so what's the
difference between just ordinary
rationality and and let's say collective
rationality and dialogue and dialogue
OHS alright so let's let's well let's do
it first what's the difference between
sort of ordinary or comp the common
right good notion of rationality and
there and the notion I'm arguing for and
then we'll do that sort of individually
because that will give me an analogic
basis for them talking about the
collective it is that okay great yeah so
typically and I know this because I
teach I teach on rationality and so I
get to see people's and these are right
educated young people they're right and
so they're sort of the best represented
representative of what we call folk
psychology so within the COG SCI
academic world folk psychology is the
psychological the implicit largely
implicit psychological theories that
most people are carrying around so
people have theories implicit theories
about intelligence
right right right and it's folk
psychology they haven't listened
theories about how memory works they
have insisted theories about what
concepts are the now one thing we should
put on the table right away is and this
is what I said a lot of time doing in
introduction to cog sign is most of
those folks psychological intuitions
have turned out to be wrong but they
have turned out to be very wrong and for
a kind of important reason right so so
let's say you know our ideas about
rationality or ideas about wisdom yeah
ideas about intelligence you know all of
them are distorted or a very yep yeah
very very skewed are these about memory
let me give you an example for
commemorate because it's it's far enough
away from our topic that'll be a little
less controversial a little a little
easier to dip sort of establish so many
people we have all these metaphors in
fact that to speak this we think of
memory as like like like a room in which
we store things and we go in there and
we retrieve it and we search through our
memory and so the metaphor we have is
kind of like we'd like a library and
we're sending people in and they're
moving around
and why and this kit brings me to the
point I wanted to make we have these
folks psychological notions because we
have to remember that in our folk
psychological context we are not
primarily interested in explaining
phenomena we're interested in primarily
predicting and training so right
there's a language of explaining in a
language of the training okay here's
what I want to say if I want to train
your memory it's a really good thing to
use that idea of a room right here's a
this is you see it on Sherlock right you
have your you have your memory palace or
your mind Palace right you have this
room it's called the method of low-side
and I say I'm gonna talk to Andrew
enough but first talk about rationality
so you know III get a room or like a
space maybe this house that I mean I'm
Phil you familiar with it the library is
where I'm gonna talk to Andrew but
rationality so form an image of you in
the library and there's books and
there's knowledge and alright right and
then and then I'm not going to talk to
you know Andrew perhaps about
transformation well that's the kitchen
on a picture Andrew in the kitchen and
he's he's doing and so what I do is I
make all these images and they're in
different places and what I do is I
actually search I go from room to room
to room in my mind there's a powerful
way to train memory the ancient orders
could use this technique to memorise
speeches that will last like six hours
so it's really powerful way to train
your memory it's and it goes very well
with all those metaphors the thing is
our memory doesn't work like that at all
that's good language for training it but
you you don't actually have that sort of
you know search cereal search because
for example can you please tell me
Justin Bieber's phone number mmm no no
you don't know you don't know it no you
didn't scroll through all of your phone
numbers and realize that it wasn't there
you just know is that like a heuristic
or something or well no there's it's
it's it's that it's there's a heuristic
there's also a kind of parallel search
there's a kind of memory probably in
neural networks as opposed to located
memory like in standard computers and
and you know and your memories aren't
stable
you're constantly reconstructing them
you're constantly rewriting them that's
why confident I listen it alright
confident eyewitness testimony
forty-nine percent of it is inaccurate
for
9% of it is wrong huh right because
confidence measures how meaningful you
find the experience not how accurate
that it is or you know we think you know
in a library things that are you know
that are relevant to each other are
stored close to each other but like in
your memory if I give you a if I say
color red say another color as quickly
as you can so red red okay or say
another color red blue okay now give me
a word that rhymes with blue true okay
so red is close to blue and blue as
close to true is red close to true no no
memory so although we talk about memory
I'm in training with that and it seems
so intuitive to us that that must be how
memory works
that's not how memory actually works you
see that I'm trying to show you just in
these sort of Pony eat you know dog and
pony examples that your memory doesn't
actually work that way in fact it's
taken us a long and and attention
doesn't work just like the spotlight and
all kinds of yeah so I'm jumping ahead
to say that this is what you mean about
wisdom - right is seeing for yourself
deception right
or are these these forms can leave their
lead to self-deception or they can lead
to a greater understanding that
depending how we use them or how
transparent they are to us right so
though what I'm trying to get at yes I
that's I think a very appropriate way of
reframing what I'm saying if we don't
pay attention to the difference between
our folks like a logical language of
training and our scientific language of
explaining we can equivocate we can
confuse them together and thereby deeply
deceive ourselves now I and get into all
kinds of New Age nonsense
well mu Age nonsense but also we could
fail to more powerfully even use our
memory when we're studying for a test so
so people think well the best way to
study for a test to sort of read the
material over and over again and
rehearse it because it's like sort of
you know writing over and over again on
the same spot in the library to make it
to be
but that's not the best way to try and
study for a test for example because
you're not actually using your memory
for how it actually functions oh can I
can I just do a slight aside here yeah
because this is fascinating to me I was
talking to Zach Stein yeahi Santino's
act you know yeah just that could I have
talked yes yeah he's a brilliant guy
anyway he told me that his that he's a
high achieving dyslexic yes and he
described his mind and it seemed to be
very similar to mine and I'm pretty sure
that I have the same thing that he has
oh you read the paragraph first and then
you read the sentence and then you read
the word you don't read from the word up
to the paragraph like you got your two
in the Gestalt and then it's sorry then
you have to get to the to the junk you
to the feature right yeah so an ordinary
mind kind of for most I shouldn't say
ordinary because nobody has an ordinary
mind but most people kind of build up
from from maybe the feature to the
gestalt and then a person who has it
sort of has that kind of dyslexia it
doesn't mean they can't read or anything
they just kind of do things in a
different you know different way you
it's a little it's a it's a little bit
more complicated everybody I'm sure
everybody actually simultaneously again
because you're not doing things
step-by-step the way we think in
language yeah here's you know so that's
why we had to get neural networks to
solve what's called the chicken and egg
problem because when I'm reading I to
read the letters in order to read the
word but I need to know what the word is
in order to disambiguate the letters
so you're spontaneously going from
feature to Gestalt and Gestalt to
feature sure right so it's in parallel
again which is not something that's easy
to put into words right it's kind it
doesn't go well with sort of again a
folk psychological understanding of how
we do things
but it's modeled well than neural
networks for example now the thing is of
course everybody's sort of doing that
but there is variation on wit like how
it's skewed some people more skewed
equally some people are more skewed
Gestalt II if you'll allow other weird
yeah so my main point of all of this and
thank you because you've helped me sort
of explicate my point right in this
discussion we've just had
is we have to be willing to challenge
our folks psychological notions
rationality yeah because there's right
it's very plausible that like all of our
other folks psychological constructs
well it has some important truths to it
it also has a lot of misrepresentation
and misdirection with respect to the
phenomenon mm-hmm and so why that's a
little bit more challenging for us I
think is is that you know if you if you
have sort of a memory that's not that
great it's a little bit affects your
sort of status and your self-esteem a
little bit but you know I'm not that
much but these terms
intelligence rationality and wisdom they
carry with them a tremendous aspects of
our cognition very very powerful so
that's why people get very very sore
about notions of intelligence
rationality and wisdom so again we need
to pull apart right our identification
with these processes which of course we
should address eventually but we need to
pull that apart from our attempt to get
our best understanding of them because
again our eye dentist like all of our a
lot of our my side biases and our
egocentric bias identification with
these processes can actually deeply
impede us getting a good understanding
of them I needed to say all of that
precisely uncurls I want to challenge
choose standard notions of what it is to
be rational okay go for it okay so one
notion of what rationality is you know
it's kind of the Spock version for the
FRA for those of you you and I have that
generation we know right this idea that
- that rationality is illogicality and
you see this in you know there's a lot
of sort of online forums that sort of
that's the model of rationality that
rationality is to be as logical as
possible and mr. Spock sort of
exemplified that and the problem with
that is it we have to we have to set it
into an overarching idea that ultimately
we're gold
we're seeking goals we're seeking to
achieve goals and so one thing we have
to note is that what rationality means
method as a method for us is we're
looking for the most reliable and
systematic way of achieving our goals
mm-hmm so you say Lao but that's fine
logic is the most reliable and
systematic way of achieving truth the
problem with that is it's not true not
because logic isn't relative relevant to
rationality but you can't identify
rationality with logic and here's the
problem logic works in terms of
certainty and a completely formal system
mm-hmm and what that means and I'm try
not to trip I try not to presuppose too
much be presumptuous of what people have
seen of this series but what that means
is you basically into a kind of
processing that has to check all of the
problems faced it has to check all of
the information it has to check all the
possible options you have to be
comprehensive and exhaustive you have to
be kind of like a machine of some kind
rather over human yeah but no machine
can do that like even or even our best
chess playing machines can search all
the possible options it's common
tutorial explosive they can't search all
of these like that this is the problem
of search is it still the profound
problem is that it's there's just too
much too much information too much so if
you and everybody knowledge is this who
was working within rationality Herbert
and Simon you know I think was was it
Simon's book I think it was a Newell and
Simon or Simon's book I think bounded
rationality their rationality is always
bounded in terms of what's actually
possible for us Jania talked about we're
in the finitary predicament and this
goes to the core of my work
we can't reason we can't make inferences
on the basis of all possible options all
possible probabilities right all
possible information that's common
entirely explosive so what we do is we
bound it we zero in on what's salient
you knew I was going to do this then
relevant then what's right and and so
that means before you can even use logic
you have to have pre logical processes
of problem formulation the direction of
attention Sergent memory and those are
not obstacles to be
rational because they prevent you from
being fully logical they actually
facilitate they constitute you being a
viable cognitive agent if you don't have
that you're going to be sick then that
the next text I try to perform I'm gonna
hit combinatorial explosion and then
I've committed cognitive suicide mm-hmm
so I for dreaming or something like that
you know a dream is is we don't normally
think of a dream as is being rational it
could be but it could it could have a
rational function or I could have yes oh
you mean well more than that I mean I
think that what you see is but one
plausible account of what dreaming does
is it's a kind of optimization process
on how your brain is operating mm-hm and
so it's not so much the content of the
dream but it's sort of the way in which
your brain is sort of practicing getting
better adjusting what it finds salient
and relevant so it does weird variations
on patterns that you've sort of acquired
through the day and it sees which one of
those sort of optimize its ability to
track and predict and solve problems
that's what you're often solving your
problems in your dreams right right here
right and so and that that looks I'll
sort of create it's all illogical but it
could turn out to be rational because it
could be actually optimizing this
process of relevance realization it is
so central especially and here's what I
want to come back if it systematically
and reliably improves your ability to
zero in on relevant information and then
I'm going to add something to that that
is directly implied by that it
systematically reliable in
systematically and reliably improves
your ability to overcome self-deception
then I think that's how we should
understand rationality well rational
practice is a practice that
systematically and reliably improves
your ability to overcome self-deception
and to optimize your ability to zero in
on the relevant information such that
you are more and more capable of being a
good general problem solver and
achieving your goals and that's what
rationality means so it's not logic
ality but it's also not just being
intelligent right because um with
intelligence is intelligence is
basically uh Leo and I argue this leo
Ferrara and I argue
and I think you can make a good case
that a lot of people are implicitly
arguing for this that what we're
measuring when we're measuring
intelligence is we're measuring sort of
your working memory capacity to zero in
on relevant information and hmm the
problem with that is and this is the
issue right very often what I what I
initially might find relevant or salient
is actually a kind of bullshitting it's
actually taking me away right from being
able to solve the particular problem I'm
paying attention to the wrong things
because my machinery is designating
certain things as relevant or salient
that actually will not help me to zero
in on or track the patterns that I need
in order to find my goals right this is
where you need insight because when you
have an AHA experience you realize oh no
I formulated the problem the wrong way
and I've got to change what I find
relevant and salient and that means if
we have an account of rationality in
which insight does not play a central
role we do not have a good account of
insight because the machinery of insight
is the machinery by which you optimize
your ability to zero in an information
and it's the same machinery you used to
overcome self-deception mm-hmm so the
problem with that with the with the the
the idea of it just being intelligent is
rationality so intelligence is what
you're using well there's a lot of if I
could just there's a lot of very stupid
intelligent people right they have the
machineries all there but they're not
using it correctly or that's right
they're not using it in an optimized way
or in a and let's say essica way or in a
we're on or or an on self-delusional way
right a kit right and so that's exactly
my point Andrew they're they're they're
your you use your intelligence to solve
your problems but that can generate all
kinds of skewed salience landscapes
capacities for acting immorally for
acting in a self deceptive manner
rationality is what you use in order to
deal with all of that right all of those
if you've side effect is generated by
using your intelligence in an adaptive
manner so rationality is is is a
practice rather than something you're
just born with oh yes that's very
important to think to know that right
that something and it's you said it was
aspirational right it's yes yes become a
rational person even though it seems
like an ideal like it's not a very
likely scenario that you would become
100% rational yeah I don't I I don't
even know if that's possible yeah I
don't I don't yeah I don't even know
that's the correct way to frame it
because it it brings with it a sense of
an idea of completeness or finality and
because your relevance really because
your intelligence is a self-organizing
evolving dynamical system and because
the world is a self-organizing dynamical
system there's no there's no sort of
final state you can get into where you
can stay where you can pronounce now I
am forever free from all process sort of
it's all process well this is this is
how I interpret the first noble truth of
Buddhism I'm not a Buddhism but like
even though you know Alexander says I am
but right because but I interpret it as
you know not that all of life is
suffering is that makes no sense but
that no matter where you turn there is
no place in which you can be free from
the threat of self deceptive
self-destructive behavior no matter how
smart you are no matter how intelligent
you are yeah you only missing something
wouldn't you you'd always have a blind
spot somewhere oh I have a lot of blind
spots a lot of them so you know you take
a look a lot of psychology is going
through the replication crisis results
aren't getting replicated well you know
what is robustly getting replicated time
and time again all this stuff about
cognitive bias all this stuff about
self-deception all this stuff about how
intelligence is necessary but not
sufficient for rationality all of that
is very very robust it is not going
through the road application crisis it's
an aspect of our cognition that we
should have very strong confidence in
which means given these two points we
should not think of rationality as
identical to either logic ality or
either to our intelligence of sort of
our innately given
problem solving capacity because that's
what I think intelligence is and and and
and I think this would actually
ameliorate a lot of useless debates
people don't like the idea you know that
IQ is fixed because then they think
they're doomed right they think oh no
right because you know and then there's
all these objections and right and but
and this is I think this is an argument
I get from Stanovich we shouldn't be
caring so much about intelligence yeaji
is a good predictor it's one of our best
measures of general intelligence you
know what I should all I really care
about about you how rational you are
because that's gonna predict how moral
you behave how how how you can overcome
ego centrism how you're less self
deceptive like an you're motruk like
what about the whole effective world
right I was you know I was thinking
about how how when I was talking to guy
last night he kind of lives in that kind
of a realm he's he's very rational as
well but but he doesn't he doesn't he
doesn't swim in rational arguments he he
kind of swims in something else or or
well but but oh but again I guess I'm
I'm I'm still I still have this narrow
definition of rationality when I know
but that's but that's great what you
just that's a beautiful segue for me
because the the so I've two ways in
which are the folk psychological notion
is to narrow it either identify and it
often does it both in a contradictory
manner but it often identifies
rationality with being intelligent yeah
right and right and therefore fix like
intelligence but not it's not
rationality is not intelligence and
rationality is developmental you can get
better and better at matter you conspire
and it's not equivalent erotic to logic
ality just being good at logic is not
it's evidence is clear it does not make
you very rational actually rationality
is about knowing where when it's about
rate rationing it's about knowing where
when and to what degree to be logical
you know this brings what you just said
brings me up to the Third Way in the
folk psychological notion ours not cross
culturally but ours in the West is
deficient is we limit rationality to
just inferential processes about belief
right
say oh we limited job could use some of
my terminology we limit rationality to
just propositional knowing and that were
the goal the sole goal of rationality is
to get true beliefs which of course is
ridiculous
I could get in you know an indefinitely
a large number of true beliefs in my
room by you know
you know noting correlations between how
many paper clips are in the room and how
many cups are in the room like the
amount of information in this room the
amount of true information is
overwhelming what we actually want is
true information that's relevant to us
relevant to our problem-solving tasks
relevant to our moral undertakings etc
yeah I was listening to somebody was
talking about intelligence I put that in
the article I write it and he said that
wisdom is when you can say so what like
you're you can discard all that
information which is important and you
could vote you can narrow in on what
really matters well yes in a deep
existential way not not on on on proton
you know as you say products or or yeah
I mean sometimes our goals are genuinely
epistemic we want to know the true
causes of things but and this is the
point I want to make but if we bring in
the many other ways in which we try to
couple ourselves to reality our
procedural knowing well that our
procedural knowing well then we want
systematically in reliable ways of
getting and improving our skills or
perspectival knowing well then we want
systematically and reliable way of
improving our right our salience
landscaping and our ability to generate
a sense of right presence our
participatory knowing we want systematic
and reliable ways of getting into the
best right kind of existential mode for
example shall they be in the having mode
right now should I be in the being mode
should I be treating you categorically
should I be treating you into it like
all of those kinds of things and how am
i appropriately set you see in the thing
about guy his guy is swimming right
first of all relevance is not cold
calculation it's not logic relevance is
about an act of commitment I am
committing my precious time and
resources in a gamble a risky gamble
that this I care I'm caring about this
information
rather than that information because I'm
ultimately trying to take care of myself
and take care of this word care seems
very important because you know one of
the reasons some people would would you
know want to be trans rational or have
you know post rational experiences or
have experiences that we're not what
they would consider to be rational with
is because rationality often seems like
a cold form of but but you're saying
exactly the opposite right I'm saying
exactly opposite so the abuse and this
goes back to Socrates so the Socratic
platonic tradition like all of this you
know there's argumentative stuff the
inferential stuff is bound up with also
abilities to change perspective to
cultivate software so that you know a
kind of salience lens that's what we
that's one of the cardinal virtues we
usually translate it very poorly as
moderation but it's much more like your
salience landscaping has evolved so it
spontaneously self-organizes to tempt
you towards what is more true towards
more right it's basically your
perspectival knowing has been trained so
that you're much less subject to
right so you usually were yeah
this is something you said in the series
usually we're tempted to what I
like you saying what if we were tempted
to do the good the good or whatever that
might be
and wouldn't and wouldn't that be part
of what a wise person has they they
would come into a situation right and
and before they're getting into perhaps
any specific inferential processing
they're sort of drawn to what's not only
what's relevant but what's you know well
you know in a problem-solving sense but
maybe what's also relevant in a moral
sense what needs to be addressed you see
that's the thing about Socrates right
and the Platonic tradition right all of
that argumentative stuff is bound up
with love it's profoundly so we see
these you know post romantic tradition
we see these as a potent well you know
spirituality is about love and science
is about reason and the two are opposed
and they're separate but no in the whole
Neil clip Socratic Neoplatonic tradition
they're bound up together in fact
Socrates you know Socrates claimed to
no to erotica he he knew what to care
about he did he did there are some
things he actually did claim to know he
that's a good definition of wisdom isn't
it - no what - yes no so he he was
seeking a rationality of appropriate
caring right now that killing can be
caring for the truth it can be also
caring for by caring about what's right
it can be caring about right what's
beautiful you see all and a lot of the
Socratic dialogue is not about coming to
an argumentative conclusion trying to
bring in the perspectival and
participatory knowing right and and
that's why Socrates often doesn't use
analogies to argument you have to use
his analogies to skills because
procedural knowledge is a little bit
closer than propositional knowledge due
respect honorable and participatory
right and so he's trying you're bringing
into perspective on than the
participatory knowing because you're
trying to shape it again you often the
dialogues don't end in any kind of
inferential conclusion they're often or
else they often leave you oh we don't
know we don't have any clear conclusion
about well it's like if I guess it's
like it's like good art or something it
doesn't yes
it doesn't wrap up the whole story so
you're you you're satisfied with your
product in like a like a Hollywood movie
it it kind of opens a new Vista for you
it opens a new Vista and it all so it
also launches you on to aspirational
transformation so what you'll see at the
end of a lot of these dialogues is
there's no argumentative conclusion but
you'll see that so right there'll be a
there's a dialogue on courage and
there's two people arguing and it's
interesting because their argument
courage and they represent these two
positions I'm talking about there's a
general and he thinks just his common
sense notion of what courage is that's
that's the crutch so we are every day
yeah right he's folk psychological and
then there's a guy who's a sophist and
he has this sort of technical sort of
logical definition right that he's heard
from somebody else right and Socrates
rejects both of those and and and then
you get to the end and there's no
conclusion as to what courage is other
than the fact that these two approaches
have been shown to be inadequate but
what you see is both of the generals say
they want their sons to come and learn
from Socrates to spend time with
Socrates because that the process well
maybe because maybe perhaps courage is
is not something that you can define
it's something that it's it's not
something you you could define in any
absolute sense no and maybe think about
Heidegger and and and what he talked
when he talked about thinking and how
how you know concepts a true concept is
something that doesn't have any kind of
finitude to it it just reveals itself
more and more over time more and more
truth over time and and and and you
can't ever pin pin it down or that's
what I'd let goes back to what I was
saying earlier about you have to get
away from models that see completeness
and I mean the image thing and I think
that's exactly the right well so
Socrates the point of the dialogue is
you have to step back and this is my
Plato writes dialogues as opposed to
just straight arguments the point is the
you you can't get a definition of
courage but as you watch Socrates move
between these two positions the skill ax
and Charybdis of going along you get a
sense of how to get on the track how to
aspire to courage and that Socrates is
reliably honest so you develop a kind of
trust in following Socrates because he
has exemplified even though he can't
explicate courage hmm so the idea that I
would like to bring into a lot of
current practices like guys circling is
to not always just be participating in
the process but also to step back and
look at what we're exemplifying in the
process so like you know and certainly
you're doing all these things to
maintain the flow of the distributed
cognition mmm-hmm and everybody is
feeling that it's very meaningful but
whatever you step back and say yeah but
what is meaning what is meaning in this
situation what and not just abstractly
because you've got the phenomenology as
active its engaged and you have multiple
people there that have multiple
perspectives on it and you can start
doing something like the surprise
dialogue well what is it to be
meaningfully connected and then and then
what you can do is check with you know
are we still exemplifying the phenomena
we're trying to explicate inside exist a
new you try to keep the two by
tightly coupled together so you don't
you constantly moving Chris master
Pietro and I talked about this in the
chapter we wrote on dr. Theo logos you
constantly sort of you've got your
constant moving but in an integrated
fashion between fear theory and theory
abut ween you know theorizing and then
going back and really theory oh really
loosing it out and yeah yeah yeah really
extremely experienced in it in action
mm-hmm and so rationality again is would
be for collective intelligence would be
to try and find systematic and reliable
ways of getting that kind of pattern of
communication and connection between
people in place hmm very very
interesting yet it seems to me that
that's very important now especially
because we're in a very anti rational
time or cyclic everything is about
sensation and feeling and I don't want
to be a you know say that feeling is bad
but but everything is about everything
is based on you know clicks and like
civilians experience and salience yeah
right yeah yep
yeah so that seems to be very important
- yeah okay that you know there's the
ocean of experience and then there's
also stepping out and coming back in and
going in and out of that mmm I think
it's very needed and I would want to I
wouldn't want to say that let's use the
Socratic model we just had and also some
of the points we've made I think our our
time is irrational or lacking in
rationality in two senses and once they
don't like it general the one general
who just let's go with my intuition and
my impulse and whatever just sort of
comes to me and then we have no no let's
be rational let's be tell you exactly
what I was gonna say as well yeah yeah
it's this this hyper rationality which
is is I don't think it's rationality at
all which you would say is not
rationality don't right yeah I still
have this deaf I still have the folk
definition of rationality in my head so
it's almost hard for me to have the
conversation until I
redefine the term rationality I complete
myself and like I said you're struggling
against not only just sort of the
familiarity of your folks psychological
conception you're also struggling
against the fact that we have set up all
these cultural patterns of
identification and evaluation around
these terms right and we reward people
and we claim this and we claim that and
that's also I think acting as an
obstacle to trying to get back to a
notion of rationality that actually
starts to overlap with wisdom you see
that's what they these two needs do this
notion of rationality is just being sort
of you know practical you know
intelligence problem-solving or the
notion of rationality is just being sort
of good logic allottee it tells me
nothing about wisdom basically it
doesn't really help me it doesn't help
me with that systematic and reliable way
of cutting through yeah heading
to what's relevant and then also
aspiring write properly aspiring so that
my development is constantly evolving
with reality in a in a sort of
continuous coupling none of that is
given to me by those models so you talk
to you in McGilchrist recently oh my god
so I I you know I'm very interested
because you know your story is almost
the opposite of his but you're probably
saying the same thing you know he talks
about it he talked about left-brain
right-brain you talk about opponent
processing their lunch working together
those seem to be kind of analogous
whereas he says that rationality is just
cutting the worlds up into bits and
turning us into bureaucratic monsters
and and we need to get more into the
right brain world of you know so a
feeling and and and you know or context
and and the right of the experience the
embodied experience of life you know and
so how did you how did your conversation
go how did you you we're going to talk
again it went so well we really clicked
really deeply so you know rebel wisdom
they recorded it it will be released at
some point
so a couple points on that first of all
because this goes to what we were
talking about earlier perhaps a more
helpful way to think of right and left
is to think and and I actually brought
this up with the in in person and he
said it was completely convergent with
him so I have good reason to believe I
can speak sort of uh something that we
are agreeing on because when I have
in-person evidence right to say so you
can because I came at it I hadn't read
Ian's work until about two weeks before
I met was gonna meet it oh okay
cuz I came at this stuff and I came to
similar conclusions from all the work I
do on insight right inside problem
solving so a good way to think about the
right hemisphere is its it way it works
more in terms of the gestalt yes exactly
yeah and and so it likes wide open
attention and it looks for for like for
for it's sort of pursuing pattern
completion right right
whereas the the left hemisphere is more
feature aliy oriented and it does things
in a step by step matter it's doing it's
doing something more like a pro running
a program than trying to complete a
pattern it's sort of building features
up step by step by step right and so
think about the kind of a tenth
attention it needs it needs very narrow
focused it looks for clarity you're over
it doesn't like ambiguity now here's the
idea of rationality when you live in the
left brain but not that next eat and and
that and that's I think part of our
Cartesian heritage that's to identify
rationality with analysis and Mary Cohen
has brought this point up and I think to
you identify rationality with analysis
is a mistake I think it's it well for
all the reasons I've already articulated
it truncates what rationality should
mean especially because rationality is
vote ratio finding the patterns
rationing right getting the getting the
proper context it's a it's a much more
logistical notion so why do we have
these two well
the left hemisphere is very good for
well-defined problems problems in which
you have a really good representation of
your initial state your goal state what
then what actions and obviously I
already know it tells you and already
know about what you already know
yeah it's familiar to you in a deep way
so a multiplication problem would be for
many people a very well defined familiar
problem now compare that to the problem
of avoiding predation yeah what does
that look like well I'm avoiding you
know well you know what's my initial
state I'm not sure right right you don't
get a notepad and start you know what
the goal state looks like right very
clearly and this is the thing and do
most of our real-world problems this is
why that that notion of rationality of
analysis is so limiting most of our
real-world problems are actually like
the problem of predation they are
ill-defined problems you and I are
trying to have a good conversation right
now
mm-hm what's the initial condition well
we're not talking that's not very
helpful what's the what's the what's
what's the goal state look like well I
don't know the art does every good
conversation look the same no they have
some feature what should I say what
should i do should i rave my hand show
you raise my voice should I like watch
it like right you see what I mean or go
on a successful first date or tell a
joke you can't draw a picture to tell
somebody this is how you go on a
successful first date you can't go for a
to be yeah can't give a program program
Yeah right but you can't that doesn't
mean it's useless there are way we get
better at going on dates we get better
at conversation and think about that
think about that what I just said how
that goes back to what Socrates is doing
in the dialogues right you get better at
becoming courageous right but that
doesn't mean I can give you a formula or
a program for an orange Yeah right
now when I when I was talking to eat
with like said we we earlier so Ian
makes a distinction it's kind of the
reverse of the distinction I make so it
I think it was it was largely somatic he
actually makes a distinction between
rationality and reason Yeah right
exactly that's what I wanted to bring
yeah and I picked up on this reason is
great because reason is full
and now you you put everything together
and we should be reasonable but but but
we're over emphasizing rationality and
cutting bits here's what I could say
then very clearly I'm using rationality
the way en uses reason exactly using
reason the way I use rationality right
so what he rejects is what I consider to
be that truncated folks like a logical
notion of rationality that I think does
not represent anything that will help
facilitate our aspiration towards wisdom
hmm hmm so although there is a problem
maybe the problem I'm seeing is that
that that notion of rationality is so
deep it's like it's Cartesian it's woven
into its woven into the scientific
worldview it's woven into our
epistemological models and those that
worldview and those epistemological
models get woven into our psychological
models they're woven into Freud they're
woven into young they're woven into many
yeah that's that's why you that's why
you that's why guy is so attracted to
Heidegger because Heidegger is like he's
profoundly trying to break out of that
whole Cartesian way of thinking about
belief and truth and rationality and
he's trying I think to get us back to a
way of understanding rationality kind
so maybe what he calls thinking this is
called rationality totally Tobin
Heidegger calls thinking and what he
McGilchrist calls reason yes yes just
sending different semantic areas here or
yes I agree agree so the the argument
that I have sort of why I think
rationality is actually an appropriate
word is reason tends to be associated
with reasoning that's wrong with reason
it's equivocal it can go to reasoning
which means inference and argument go to
reasonable which means this kind of
thing we're talking about so that's why
I'm a little bit whereas the
etymological origin of rationality is
Rati oh it's finding proportion that's
it's putting things into proper relation
it's getting the proper perspective it's
a relationship yeah exactly it's more
about pattern completion then
then running a program to completion
those are two very very different things
also we need to be unreasonable at times
look II mean by that because I well we
need to as you say break frame right so
for I'm trying to be reasonable all the
time if you know this is why there's
shaman is there the you know there were
shamans and you know - as you talked
about in your series yeah break out of
the yeah nine dot problem or yep so but
this brings me to this brings me to an
important point I would want to say
because I actually I actually have
brought this argument up I presented at
a conference at a couple conferences
this idea that disruptive strategies are
actually important for optimization
in fact there's systematically and
reliably important for optimization so
if you're running a neural network for
example you just let it just sort of run
right it'll over fit to the data it'll
it'll find patterns in its sample and
really pick up on those patterns in its
sample that don't actually generalize
generalize to the population you know
there's a sampling bias right and so
because the machines are so powerful and
your brain is way more powerful than any
neural network so think about how you
can really zero in right and get bound
to you can over fit to your particular
sampling of data so what do you do in
the neural networks well you you
actually disrupt the network you shut
off some you shut off half the nodes or
you throw noise or static into the
system
and what that does is it makes the
neural network we self organize right
and that we've stuff organization
actually allows it to now generalize in
ways it couldn't generalize before yeah
so you have to throw disruption in I
recently did some graph breathing
technique he's like that and I I don't
do psychedelics but but but that kind of
experience just it throws you into these
wild sort of spaces right right and it's
wild and that and then you come out at
the other side is if you've gone into
Alice in Wonderland and you come out the
other side sort of like and you have to
reassemble your ordinary existence and
hopeful
you've got some insight after doing that
yeah and what what happens is your
perspectival and participatory knowing
have been shifted and so a new course of
development is actually available to you
yeah think about think about like when
you're in that when you're in that space
it's like what happens in dreams a lot
of variations are being thrown out like
sort of generated
options are being created that open up
what's called the state space it opens
up the possibilities that that your
brain can actually get itself into like
your brain is a machine that's
constantly making itself into a new kind
of machine and you want to periodically
like with a neural network you want to
open up the options it can consider not
only the options in the world it can
consider but the options for what kind
of machine it can be it's those two
together at the same time and so if it
and you can see this even an insight
problem-solving if I give you an insight
negate and I moderately distract you or
even throw some static into the picture
some noise that will actually help to
trigger your insight of course yeah okay
so get better at the game right if
you're tripped up but yeah but do it the
right way they 2000's right so there's
an X there's a kind of expertise or you
have to do it in the right way right
there's no formula but you have to do in
the right way but there are systemic and
reliable ways of getting better at doing
that disruption
now here's my argument this disruption
is really indispensable to optimization
there are systematic and reliable ways
of doing that wouldn't that therefore be
integral to our account of wisdom that
these disruptive processes and that
means that although they're non
inferential they have actually no
propositional content whatsoever because
they're basically oh yeah zero
propositional content right but
nevertheless they move you towards a
more optimal that optimization of you
know I have more options in what kind of
cognitive being I can be yeah and where
are more options about what kind of
world I can dwell within and that is
making you more rational yeah and well
if yeah again it's counter into it
yeah well I guess the rational world
that we live in often feels like a kind
of prison right yes we're trapped in
caught conceptual models of things and
that's one of the reasons why you would
you know you would you would want to
break frame or you do fasting or you
know or going into nature and you know
have all kinds of let's say of those
kind of experiences well this brings me
to another point and and you know I
think Ian's bang on about the left and
right stuff but there's another there's
another opponent process that we need to
bring into the discussion here which is
the relationship like because we're
constantly toggling between being task
centered and mind wandering right and
the and the point of mind wandering I
would argue at least one of its funny
wondering oh yeah it's to break frame
it's - its - its to bring in some mild
distraction take you into a weird so
that's key again our guy sorry I keep
saying he because I'm in France but I
think that's that's what guy does well
see I did it was about wandering so what
he's trying to do is you know I think
what Heidegger is doing is you know you
just stay on the path that's like the
machine that's gonna over fit right and
what you need to do is you need to
wander a bit right you need to go off
almost like in mind-wandering and what
that does is allow you to you know
introduce the noise introduce some
variation break some frame so that so
but you keep moving forward but you're
now actually improving your
connectedness to the world rather than
just getting to your destination on your
part yeah and now that also speaks to
the pathology of modernity right is that
we don't maybe we don't wander enough we
don't we don't want enough han says we
don't we fill up the space too much with
with with you know information yeah
and salience and and we that's why I
also pointed out Hans notion of
lingering it's not only that we fill up
this space we right we
well take Heidegger being at a time that
your being isn't inherently temporal
right and so you are wait you are
respectable and participatory knowing of
time because you don't know time in any
other way right the Augustine famously
said this I know what time is until
somebody asks me what it is because
right you only know time by being in
time right by being a temporal thing but
so your existential mode with respect to
time how you're experiencing that's the
wrong word that's the only word I have
how you're participating maybe let me
use that word how you're participating
in time existentially has a huge impact
on the kind of being you can be and so
hans point is we are moving into a
culture in which we can't leader we
can't we can't we can't flow with things
wait everything is atomized we're going
down slike minutes and seconds is his
cut up that's exactly the idea - yeah
mm-hmm and so you don't get any flow you
get you get the you get sort of the
salient second right you know um so a
lot of people have met talked to me
about this and you know we're seeing
we're seeing this consistent trend
towards the death of melody in popular
music that we're losing melodic
complexity and there's this compressed
sound all the time with mp3 it's extreme
compression of sound and supremes
compression of sound and salience in
salience and intensity are taking up the
place of right complexity and
development you don't have to follow a
long piece of music and go through all
kinds of transformation you can
instantly without effort get sort of hit
by the same product right yes exactly
you know and that's and so what that
means for us is yeah that like I said
it's also that we can't linger we can't
stay with things in a way that affords
us remembering the projects of
aspiration yeah I think I've liked going
to the galleries like I live near in
Paris and there's all these galleries
and how many people look at a painting
you know how many people go into and
actually
just stay with the painting and look at
the painting and and find out a valuable
experience right yes most people would
would would would sort of you know look
at the painting and like take a picture
snapshot of it with their iPhone and say
I'd been there and I've seen that
painting what but but that that goes to
just what I said the point is to collect
atoms to collect moments that are
atomized and are removed from a flow of
development they're just snapshots yeah
I think I think their remedy to that one
of the remedies I've seen is probably
meditation in some sense because yeah
for for our modern times you know I
think because it's how else can you how
else can you because there's so much
stimulus all the time how else can you
take a break from that and I think I
think I think I think both meditation
and contemplation are needed sure did
you have to break frame and make frame I
think being able to enter into the
Ilocos to enter into a conversation oh
that's another thing for me like that's
like I've been meditating for years but
but you and Guyon that's a--that's a new
kind of possibility for me right I
hadn't really thought of that so much
well I mean this is the this is part of
the platonic notion that training your
rationality in the sense I've been
arguing for and training your sociality
are deeply interpenetrating things
that's why he presents his philosophy in
a dialogue because you're not you're
those two those two things our ability
to connect to distributed cognition and
participate in collective intelligence
and collective rationality or dare I say
collective wisdom in its its in
resonance with our individual project of
aspiring to rationality and wisdom these
two things mutually afford and depend on
each other
hmm yeah yeah yeah and also
I was just sort of thinking about how
how why this sort of conversation is
compelling to people and stuff which
it's kind of a weird thing it's like a
homeless or like homeless here or
something yeah saying that to the guy
last night it's like we're putting in
these videos on YouTube it's not part of
the mainstream culture but it seems to
be there seems to be a need for it for
that kind of kind of totally I think the
the online world I mean it has it has
sort of it has some of the greatest
magnifiers of the things that exhaust
abate the meaning crisis you know but
you know you Heidegger talks about where
you know what I think he's holder lining
quotes where the danger is there they're
also right the future grows I think it's
a translation I might have missed
translator but the basic idea is you
know because it's it's a it's
destabilizing the system it's also but
also it can be an affordance of the
system going through self-transcendence
rather than disintegration you can even
say a death and rebirth of some yeah
kind of thing a shamanic kind of idea
and so what what I think what's
happening with the Chris and I talked
about the meta conversation you have all
these conversations and then what
YouTube is doing is setting up this
thing where people are having
conversations but they're doing them
with the awareness right and their
connectivity to other conversations so
there's not only idea logos within a
conversation there's this deal logos
that stay in place between all of these
conversations and the way they constrain
and impregnate and engender each other
in this kind of complex self-organizing
dynamic which is really really important
because you see the same thing again at
least analogous and the Platonic
dialogues you shouldn't just ever read
one platonic dialogue that's a mistake
you should read because you should read
all of the ecosystem again of yes all of
yes exactly all of the dialogues are
speaking to and influencing and changing
and affecting each other in powerful
ways and we're doing something and now
it gets to that here's a dialogue and
then you've won with guy and then
they're talked to each other and speak
to each other yeah now that will inform
me to speak to you and
somebody else might get a little
something out of this and bring it yeah
yeah yeah again to bring a Socratic
platonic thing and there's a possibility
for Aragog a that's that reciprocal
opening that you and I have talked about
before so the conversation when it when
it moves into dialogo so you've got the
reciprocal opening that's happening and
that of course is again a kind of love
right because people get into difficult
opening that the experience they have
the experience of the effect of state
love isn't an emotion it's a
higher-order affective state but it's a
it's an effective state and write up
love enough to get how the rationality
and the sociality and the love are all
bound together
how should I put them all back together
uh-huh got you yeah they're they're all
sort of in little islands over here and
they need to come in one place exactly
that's why that's why as critical of
Romanticism as I am of empiricism
because both of them keep although those
things apart but for different reasons
for different positions that they hold
and different epistemologies and
metaphysics and I think all of them are
therefore equally at fault for keeping
those things apart no I mean I'm doing a
bit of a you know a gloss my other
question actually I wrote that down it's
like what can we what can we take from
Romanticism because romanticism is so
powerful it's so you know that's the
thing so it's so you know we need that
and on some level especially in our you
know online world people are so blase
and stuff we we need to we don't know I
have a feeling that that we need we need
grandeur
sort of experiences and emotions that
that that were being too polite and
timid and it's it's like being in a cage
of some kind in romanticism is like
trying to break that cage a little bit
it is I mean so again I was going to
engage in some self-criticism and you've
actually allowed me to do so so thank
you for that I mean I I try to make a
distinction between what I call decadent
romanticism which is sort of a folk
psychological version of romanticize
Cheryl right and sometimes I have not
been careful enough about that and so I
do apologize to people because you have
to take a look at like just like I don't
think you should talk about
post-modernism it's like I'm sure you
should zero in on particular thinkers in
particular arguments because it's
variation and so here's what I want to
say and especially the I don't even know
I want to call them romantics that the
early the you know the early post
contents like Schlegel and people like
that I think it'll actually saying
things remarkably similar to what I'm
trying to argue for and but the
romanticism that you get especially
Russo's version of Romanticism yeah
which is a prototypical version of it is
it singable romanticism and I want to
say this I want to try and convey
something I'm gonna sit carefully
and hopefully provocatively it's closer
to the truth than the imperative that
empiricism and therefore it's think it's
more dangerous it's more dangerous
because it's not contained and it's
saying in a collective experience it's
it's sort of okay there's that so you've
got Russo's glorification of individual
subjectivity okay no that's clearly a
true self right yeah I mean he does have
stuff about the general will but when
we're talking about how he's the father
of Romanticism this the the
glorification of individual subjectivity
is there are the idea that you come with
a true self that you must be true to
which is antithetical to the idea of
aspiration so it's antithetical to the
ceramic ideal of aspiration the idea
that
this subjectivity should be thought of
because I so how am I trying what we was
talking about it he he's he does not
express enough worry about the problem
the problem of self-deception sort of
separating all of this from rationality
as I've tried to describe to describe it
right to put the Socratic notion of
overcoming the ways in which we deceive
ourselves in our self this
exploration and expression of your
individual subjectivity in your capacity
but to imagination will for imposing an
order on the world well think about how
that could just be filled with
self-deception right now you know you're
like projection and bias and Prejudice
like all of those things right and so
romanticism doesn't it's it's separated
itself off from deep concerns about
human the human proclivity for
self-deceptive self-destructive behavior
which is why we we get the almost the
romantic trope of you know how living
romantically ultimately is kind of
self-destructive of the people who try
to help to live that way you can see
that in you know sort of weathering
Heights kind of stuff right oh yeah my
mother read that book like 20 times
let's say it's so appealing to people
yeah I guess there's a self-destructive
element in that well also a hatred of
civilization or a hatred of your efforts
to to you know you know build things and
yep yep so there there is a lot of so it
was a terrific and I want even catch
both senses of that word it was a
terrific terrific strategy for breaking
the frame of empiricist enlightenment
for breaking the frame that John Locke
gave us of the tabula rasa mind and the
world imposes itself in the finger of
the world right so my mind it was a
great counteractive
that but I think it generates its own
frame that needs to be broken and broken
Bo that's well said
yeah that's great hmm-hmm that's why
Heidegger is so interested in being
because right annan challenging the idea
that we should impose our will on the
world right that the world is just a
standing reserve because the part of
what heidegger's trying to get us to
remember is you know Locke has the mind
as a blank slate but Rousseau has the
world as a blank canvas upon which we
paint our subjectivity and Heidegger is
trying to get us to remember no no it's
not a blank canvas
it's a world it is deep and profound and
beyond us yeah yeah yeah that's great
hmm and it discloses itself you know as
it will who's feyza huh I've heard two
pronunciations and I keep getting
corrected by both camps on how I should
pronounce the Greek term I was I was
broke in my intellect in my undergrad
everybody pronounced it as fuzes but
I've not been told no it's not more like
thesis or crisis or something or physics
right that's the word disclosure and I'm
hiding well where did we get physics
from but it means it means the made
which nature blossoms from itself blooms
from itself but also the way in which
nature loves to hide itself oh yeah yeah
right right yeah yeah yeah Heidegger is
another subject yeah Fitz yeah and I
mean I'm having excellent conversations
with Johannes about this and I think
it's up on his channel I'm gonna put up
the dialogue that I had with him
excellent we're gonna have enough and he
had guy and I are gonna talk shortly
about sort of Heidegger but I'm gonna
put up the dialogue I had with Johannes
I'm doing it I'm doing a couple new
series right I'm doing the minding Media
series but I'm also doing this series
I'm entitled it yet but what I'm having
just I'm trying to exemplify dialectic
which is the psycho technology of
engendering deal logos I'm trying to
exemplify that and get into these like
these discussions where we're
exemplified
and explicate a what what does
spirituality need within the scientific
worldview and the meeting crisis what
does that mean for us
uh-huh right we had an accent
conversation on Heidegger and science
and technology yeah I loved it I saw
someone half of it and I was released on
mine later the other do you think you've
said what you wanted to say about about
about wisdom and and and in rationality
and is there any Israel want to say what
sends here yeah I want to say one more
thing about sort of clarifying a bit the
relationship between wisdom and
rationality I think that we should think
of ecologies of practices for each one
of the kinds of knowing that make us
more rational so you know ecologies of
practice is for propositional knowing
economies of practices for procedural
knowing ecologies of practices for
prospective and participatory so you
have some examples well I think the
ecology of practice for propositional
knowing we've we've got I mean that's
what we and we think we know what we're
talking about when we use this term I'm
going to use but if you do any
philosophy around this we don't actually
know what we need and this is the term
science science is a whole ecology of
practices and it's bound up with history
right yeah and it's this way of trying
to get to be as rational as we can
because I the scientific method it's
actually a family of methods is not
about coming to certain conclusions it's
about really trying to reduce the
influence of self-deception on our
inferential processes and our
propositional knowing that's what
actually is going on the site science is
largely about trying to set things up so
that we can break through our patterns
of self-deception right now you have
similar things right in your procedural
knowing and this is where you know I
think the martial art traditions give us
fantastic example well how to cultivate
ecologies of practices and this is where
Rafe Kelly is just doing some amazing
and important work right
on this kind of thing not right the way
he's using parkour and integrating it
with martial art practice and
mindfulness but go and see some of the
his videos see some of the dialogues
I've had with him mm-hm the perspective
of knowing well that of course that's
where all the stuff on attention and
awareness the mindfulness practices
right the flow induction practices are
really important knowing that's where
the DLO goes that's what this is yes
okay
yeah participatory knowing we're trying
to we're trying to we're trying to alter
our not just our thoughts but our
identities the way in which we're
mutually shaping each other the way
we're being the way us and the world are
engaging so I will I'm entering into a
reciprocal opening with you but together
we're also trying to enter into a
reciprocal opening with the world right
so yeah mm-hmm great great so here's my
point there let's say there are reliable
systemic and reliable kinds of
rationality for each of the kinds of
knowing there's propositional
rationality procedural rationality
perspective of rationality and
participatory then you need something
that optimizes the relationship between
all of those rationalities hmm that's
wisdom so wisdom is about the
relationship it's about all between
between all it's about it's kind of the
whole yep okay okay I see it's kind of
it's wisdom is very much a kind of meta
rationality right yeah leads that's how
I would argue I think that I think that
it's not identical to what that like
gnosis that the world gnosis came to me
to me is that each one of them I tend to
think of APIs to me for a propositional
tech made from cloth for procedural
noesis for perspectival and gnosis for
participatory and then i think sophia
and phronesis describe the two aspects
of wisdom the bottom-up aspect that's
from esis at the top-down house so when
I when I'm coordinating those four kinds
of knowing I need a powerful I need a
lot of bottom-up and I need a lot of
top-down I need from Isis that I need
Sofia uh-huh awesome wow that's that's a
whole structure you've well you know it
goes towards the work I'm doing with
Daniel Craig on the cognitive continuum
by the way I just want to mention I have
an IndieGoGo campaign for and I'm not
getting any money from that campaign or
from the book the money is I've got a
university professor I get a salary I'm
fine Daniel the student and he's
committing to working on this book with
me and it's not on writing he's
generating art he's putting he's
basically key like the movie producer as
well as a co-author and so this money is
to help to support him as he's doing all
of this work but that what we're talking
about in the cognitive continuum is
exactly this because I think and I try
to argue that in the series I think we
can get also instead of like instead of
building a mystique around these terms
and this is where like I haven't
Thompson's work I think is really
important also Steven Bachelor both of
them are now post Buddhists because they
object to Buddhist Buddhist
exceptionalism the idea that Buddhism is
somehow a special or perverse religion
compared to all the rest because it's
somehow the scientific and I object to
that as well I I knew you would i nee
would and you have to remember that both
Steven and I know I've met Steven had
dinner with him
and evan is a colleague and friend of
mine they're both deep they're deep
friends and Buddhism these are not
hostile yeah yeah outside right and so
right they point to the fact that the
what's happened is this let's take a
term like enlightenment it's bound up
with entire cultural projects and
worldviews and it often has this
mystique around it I remember I let me
tell you how this frustrates me you know
I've asked Buddhist you know how many
people in the world do you think are
enlightened right now and they'll say
well probably no one and then it's sort
of my mom minded go but what the heck is
it for that right I mean the term is
meaningless right and so so I think
instead just like I try to if you'll
allow me I tried to reverse-engineer
wisdom I tried to build it up out of
fear right and and in terms of what we
wanted to do and Howard well I think we
should do the same thing with
enlightenment I think enlightenment is
we should reverse engineer it oh it's a
terrible word isn't it it's just it's a
terrible word and what I think we should
do is right this is how I want to use
the word and maybe we should use a
different word because because of the
critiques that Steven and especially
Evan are making but I want Amy so once I
have wisdom the two are gonna be bound
together
I want a wise ecology of practices that
it helps me transform cognition
consciousness character and communitas
so that I can systematically and
reliably overcome the perennial problems
of self-deception and self-destruction
and afford enhancing all of the
connections what I call religio that are
so constitutive in meeting in life for
me that's enlightenment because it has
to be some other deep metaphysical thing
I don't care because I want to be able
to help people alleviate you know the
suffering of the perennial problems and
afford the flourishing of enhanced
connectivity to themselves to each other
in the world
mmm yeah so you want to stay within in
the real I guess I want it and I'm going
to stipulate how I'm gonna use the term
and I'm trying so there I'm saying I'm
not using it ambiguous
I'm trying to not use it in a way that
is loaded into a particular I mean I
can't be completely free of a cultural
worldview but I'm not trying to bind it
to a particular cultural tradition
instead I'm trying to pick up on what
science gives us access to is Universal
features and principles of our cognition
and then you know the notion that is
pragmatically engineered for a specific
set of what badly and widely needed
goals hmm yeah so I guess the reason
this this term is so offensive is that
it kind of I was just thinking that it
kind of it implies a an end product or
something it's so a deeply critical of
that a deeply critical of sort of the
perfection completion aspects of the
term enlightenment are deeply critical
of that people refuse to acknowledge
that they're sliding between something
that's explaining the world and
something that's evaluating the world
right it's to use sort of technical
language and this is one of Evans
criticisms like you don't want to you
don't want to confuse your best
description of how reality is with your
your best sort of normative claims about
how things should be
those aren't those aren't the same and
so for example what why does that matter
well science isn't doing that second
thing science is not in the project uh
this is the way things should be this is
you know this is moral this is moral
excellence this is a static excellent
science isn't it it doesn't have the
machinery for doing that science is
about trying to give the best
explanations
it doesn't really afford us you know
aspirational projects and so I think
Judaism is an aspirational project and
therefore to pretend that it's sort of
like it's it's a it's also deeply
scientific ah that's a category mistake
yeah it's a category mistake for sure
it's not yeah so it's just one way of
knowing right and then Buddhism might be
another way well I think a dress is
something that science doesn't address
which is aspirational project of
transformation and self transcendence
and right and that it's gonna have a
historical cultural aspect to it right
yeah so I
what we should do what we're trying to
do what Daniel are trying to do is well
let's look at different cultural models
and then let's look at this engineering
this pragmatically engineering sense of
enlightenment that I've just given you
and let's put them into dialogue and try
and get some convergent thing that maybe
has less of the off-putting mystique of
a lot of you know when you when you talk
to people about enlightenment it's it
verges on the you know the supernatural
and the person is becoming godlike and
it's like well if that's what it is
then and I don't mean it's
disrespectfully to Buddhist but I'm not
interested in that I'm really not
interested in in and godlike people or
yeah I mean I'm interested I you know
I'm interested in the aspiration to
becoming more and more at one with sort
of the sacred depths of reality but
that's very different from it's a that's
a question of growth not a question of
some ultimate state or yes some ultimate
state and some and some ultimate
transhuman state mm-hmm so there's a bit
of a niche in critiquing in my head here
about stop Lee Jung you should be
overcoming yourself but you should never
be abandoning your humanity in that
project so we see hey I guess I guess I
guess I'm gonna say something a little
provocative here I I find humanity
ultimately good enough this is why I
love Conrad so much the heart of
darkness do you compare Marlow and Kurds
Kurds takes on the hubristic past of
becoming a god right and then he suffers
the horror of the horror the horror
Marlow makes conscious decision to act
to exercise restraint and stay with his
humanity right that he will not even
though they'll follow the journey he'll
go all the way to seeing hurts he will
never abandon his humanity that's what
the heart of darkness I think it's such
a now we're fully important well that
seems to be the Bodhisattva vow if I'm
defending Buddhism a little bit okay
sure uh-huh is is is is to do just that
isn't it it's not it's not to sate yeah
I think the Bodhisattva
well it might have been a bit of a
corrective than in Mahayana for tear
evading the because the body of October
is therefore today right much more
different than the our hat in some ways
yeah that's that's a good thought I
hadn't thought about that
but yeah the because there's a there's a
commitment to you staying with humanity
you know and and that every being is
your they call it mother being it's like
every being as your mother and and you
you have to liberate every being it's a
wild sort of idea but it's it's a sort
of wild heroic idea that's but it but
it's not very rational certainly not I
think it's rational in the way I was is
Russia here we go again it's just I
can't get the folk rationally iid out of
my head but I like that I'm sorry
implicit is a way of deeply binding the
Enlightenment project to humanity yeah
that's a good point that's a good point
injury that's a really good point i
didn't thought of that